A Los Angeles crime saga.
Heat is a crime, drama, action film directed by Michael Mann.
Obsessive master thief Neil McCauley leads a top-notch crew on various daring heists throughout
Los Angeles while determined detective Vincent Hanna pursues him without rest.
Each man recognizes and respects the ability and the dedication of the other even
though they are aware their cat-and-mouse game may end in violence.
Lt. Vincent Hanna, played by Al Pacino.
Neil McCauley, played by Robert De Niro.
Chris Shiherlis, played by Val Kilmer.
Nate, played by Jon Voight.
Michael Cheritto, played by Tom Sizemore.
Justine, played by Diane Venora.
Heat is a 1995 American crime drama film written and directed by Michael Mann.
It features an ensemble cast led by Al Pacino and Robert De Niro, with Tom
Sizemore, Jon Voight, and Val Kilmer in supporting roles.
The film follows the conflict between a Los Angeles Police Department Robbery Homicide detective, played by Pacino, and a career
thief, played by De Niro, while also depicting its effect on their professional relationships and personal lives.
Mann wrote the original script for Heat in 1979, basing it on Chicago police officer Chuck
Adamson's pursuit of criminal Neil McCauley, after whom De Niro's character is named.
The script was first used for a television pilot developed by
Mann, which became the 1989 television film L.A.
Takedown after the pilot did not receive a series order.
In 1994, Mann revisited the script to turn it into a feature
film, co-producing the project with Art Linson.
The film marks De Niro and Pacino's first on-screen appearance together
following a period of acclaimed performances from both.
Due to their esteemed reputations, promotion centered on their involvement.
Heat was released by Warner Bros.
on December 15, 1995.
The film was a critical and commercial success, grossing
$187.4 million on a $60 million budget.
Critics praised Mann's direction and the performances of Pacino and De Niro, and the film is considered to be
one of the greatest and most influential crime films of all time, inspiring several other works.
A sequel has been in development since 2022.
The film explores themes of robbery, chase, obsession, detective, heist.
The tone is dark and emotional.